Contact

Västergatan 25 Södertälje Sweden +46734808875 (Mobile) mahaboobtabriz@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/mahaboobtabriz-9a59b920 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Expertise in Aerospace as well as in Automotive Domain as a stress Analysist

Aerospace

Requirements Analysis

Certifications CATIA V5 R20 Ansys

Mahaboob Tabriz

senior Design Engineer at Scania Sweden Stockholm, Stockholm County, Sweden

Summary

I Graduated as a masters in Machine Design from Visvesvaraya technological university, Belgaum, India. Basically, as a mechanical engineer, I have a strong background in the basic principles of engineering, methods and practices in mechanical system design, testing and troubleshooting mechanical equipment. In addition, I am proficient in using GT Suite software, Catia-V5 & Auto CAD designing tools Ansys, NASTRAN,

My professional work experience as a Design Engineer in INFOTECH LTD Hyderabad and Team Leader In WIPRO TECHNOLOGIES .In industry my 14 years of Experience have given me not only a strong technical foundation but also domain knowledge and exposure to Work environment. My key strengths include effective communication, strong troubleshooting skills, Quick problem solving ability and passionate to learn and adopt new technologies and skills.

As my years of education and experience make me feel confident that I can excel and live up to the expectations in performing the duties assigned. My enclosed resume provides more details on my qualifications, skills and work experience.

Experience

Scania Group
Development Engineer at Scania
October 2022 - Present (2 years 5 months)
Stockholm County, Sweden

HKBKCE R&D

Department Head of Mechanical Engineering Department February 2014 - January 2022 (8 years) India

1.•• Evaluated performance continuously to identify areas in need of improvement and implement strategies to keep team on-track.

- Lead regular meetings with team leaders and front-line staff to convey important operational information and new targets.
- Collaborated with department personnel to coordinate multifaceted solutions to emerging problems.
- Improved department operations by capturing numerous opportunities to streamline processes and reduce waste.
- Maximized team performance by hiring, training and disciplining staff to consistently exceed expectations.
- Managed efficient workflows by creating effective schedules and delegating work based on personnel strengths and knowledge.
- Communicated with managers of other departments to maintain transparency.
- Cultivated collaborative, performance-oriented culture to keep team motivated and enthusiastic about achieving shared goals.
- Maintained organized inventory with accurate records through proper ordering, tracking and auditing procedures.
- Prepared annual budgets with controls to prevent overages.
- Worked actively with management team to create daily and weekly plans based on scenario.
- Kept employee workloads fair and balanced to achieve objectives while maintaining high job satisfaction.
- Proved successful working within tight deadlines and fast-paced atmosphere.
- Exceeded goals through effective task prioritization and great work ethic.

Wipro Technologies

Project Engineer in Automotive and Aerospace Domain June 2011 - September 2013 (2 years 4 months) Bangalore

- 1. Worked as Subject Matter Expert In computer simulation using FEA tools.
- Supported manufacturer plant SPOC on supplier payment and miscellaneous queries
- Visited regularly to the design team address all design related queries on a regular basis
- Facilitated weekly meeting with the customer organization on design specification
- Co-ordinated with the onsite team to resolve Design queries
- Organize regular meeting with the stakeholders & onsite team to review the design process & update as required
- Planning and assisting design team using CATIA V5, CAD, and 3D CAD programs.

- Performing computer simulations using ANSYS, NX software and LSDYNA and experiments to virtually test and refine the designs.
- Documenting the design process, iterations, and test analytics.
- Preparing technical reports, design specifications documents, and operational manuals.
- · Achievements:
- o Was awarded, "Best Performer of the Year (2013)"

Infotech Enterprises IT Services Pvt Ltd (Infotech IT)
Design Engineer
June 2008 - June 2009 (1 year 1 month)

Hyderabad

- Worked as Subject Matter Expert in MATHCAD and in Hand Calculation
- Conducted trainings and mentored team members on project related activities
- Explain the process flow requirements and timelines to the team.
- Communicated issues in timely manner to the Client, and assisted with their resolution
- In confidence of the Management Team, ensured team's performance to meet the objectives of the business unit within defined deadlines
- Was responsible for resource allocation, review progress of the project on a daily basis, together with the team, to ensure timely delivery of project deliverables
- Created and collected KPIs from the teams. Performed review of the data collected to ensure accuracy
- Resolved various queries on a daily basis and also provided efficient and timely solutions to complex queries.
- Completed all client assigned tasks / trainings / SOPs on time.
- Meeting with clients and design teams to determine mechanical applications and requirements
- To generate pressure loads by using MATCAD software for AIRBUS family.
- Performing computer simulations using NX software and experiments to virtually test and refine the designs.
- Generating FIRST FLIGHT CLEARNACE REPORT to deliver it to the customers.
- By using pre processor tools like HYPERMESH prepare the deck for further simulation.
- Documenting the design process, iterations, and test analytics.
- Preparing technical reports, design specifications documents, and operational manuals

Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO) Project Trainee

August 2006 - May 2007 (10 months)

India

- The project deals with redesigning of TATRA VECHILE CHASSIS by using 3D CAD tools.
- Optimizing the weight of truck chassis by performing simulation tool like ANSYS.
- Writing reports and presenting results to managers and customers.
- Ensure compliance with the industry's safety standards.
- · Maintain accurate records.
- Create cost effective designs exceeding customer expectations.
- Interact with internal resources and vendors to support prototype fabrication, assembly and validation testing.
- Assist in multidisciplinary project activities.

Achievements:

• Appreciation by Defiance organization on completion of the project within the minimum time.

Education

Visvesvaraya Technological University

Master of Technology - MTech, Machine Design · (April 2005 - March 2007)

Visvesvaraya Technological University

Bachelor of Engineering - BE, Mechanical Engineering · (April 2000 - May 2005)

Department of Technical Education Government of Karnatak Diploma in Mechanical Engineering, Mechanical Engineering · (June 1996 - January 2000)